Finding aid to the Esther Cloudman Dunn Papers CA.MS.00325
Smith College Archives
Esther Cloudman Dunn Papers
1864-1977
Smith College Archives
Dunn, Esther Cloudman, 1891-
CA.MS.00325
1.667 linear feet (4 containers)
Chairman of the English Department. Collection contains correspondence, clippings, notebooks, publications, programs, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Born in 1891, Esther Cloudman Dunn was raised in Portland, Maine. Attending Cornell University, Dunn graduated in 1913, and became the first woman to receive a Ph.D. in literature from the University of London. Prior to her tenure at Smith College, Dunn taught at Reading High School and Bryn Mawr College. Known for her research, Dunn explored Shakespeare, William Wordsworth, the Elizabethan Age, and romanticism. Dunn taught at Smith from 1922-1959, eventually becoming chairman of the college's English department. Publishing numerous books and articles, Dunn was a well-known scholar for her 1939 work Shakespeare in America. After retiring from Smith, Dunn continued to work nearly up until her 80th birthday, teaching both a graduate seminar in Washington D.C. and a course at the University of Massachusetts. Dunn passed away August 1, 1977 at the age of 86.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains correspondence, obituaries, clippings, notebooks, programs, transcripts of lectures, information about her family's apple endeavor, and photographs. Materials also included in the collection are numerous publications, including a copy of Dunn's 1920 book Inman's Portrait of Wordsworth, as well as Cloudman Hill Heritage by her brother, Charles Dunn Jr.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Esther Cloudman Dunn papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Dunn, Esther Cloudman, 1891-
- Biographical Material (Box 778)
- Index, undated (Box 778, Folder 1)
- General, 1916-1923; undated (Box 778, Folder 2)
- Obituaries, 1977 (Box 778, Folder 3)
- Portland, Maine, 1909; undated (Box 778, Folder 4)
- Cornell University, 1912-1921 (Box 778, Folder 5)
- Reading High School, 1913-1914 (Box 778, Folder 6)
- Farmington, Maine (summer school), 1915 (Box 778, Folder 7)
- Bryn Mawr College, 1913-1915; undated (Box 778, Folder 8)
- University of London, 1920-1933; undated (Box 778, Folder 9)
- Smith College, 1923-1965 (Box 778, Folder 10)
- Lectures and writings, 1930-1956; undated (Box 778, Folder 11)
- Notebooks, undated (Box 778, Folder 12)
- Personal library and course books, 1864-1960 (Box 778, Folder 13)
- Photographs, 1922-1977; undated (Box 778, Folder 14)
- Publications, 1920-1955; undated (Box 778, Folder 15)
- Publications: announcements and reviews, 1939; undated (Box 778, Folder 16)
- Publications: correspondence, 1914-1926 (Box 778, Folder 17)
- Family (Box 778)
- Cloudman Hill Heritage by Charles Dunn Jr., 1939 (Box 779, Folder 1)
- Local clippings, 1913-1920; undated (Box 779, Folder 2)
- National clippings, 1913-1923; undated (Box 779, Folder 3)
- Father, London, 1922 (Box 779, Folder 4)
- Maine: general, 1900-1936 (Box 779, Folder 5)
- Maine: apples (designs, plans, etc.), 1916-1918; undated (Box 779, Folder 6)
- Maine: Quebec Extension Railroad, 1920-1924; undated (Box 779, Folder 7)
- Photographs and photograph album, 1911-1931; undated (Box 779, Folder 8)
- Photograph: glass negative of a bull, undated (Box 779, Folder 9)
- Correspondence (Box 779)
- Charles Dunn (father), 1910 (Box 780, Folder 1)
- Charles Dunn (father), 1920-1921 (Box 780, Folder 2)
- Charles Dunn (father), 1922-1923 (Box 780, Folder 3)
- Charles Dunn (father), 1920-1924 (Box 780, Folder 4)
- Home, family, 1922-1923 (Box 780, Folder 5)
- Home, family, 1922-1933; undated (Box 780, Folder 6)
- Appointment letters, 1922 (Box 780, Folder 7)
- Smith College (appointment), 1922 (Box 780, Folder 8)
- Smith College (sabbatical), 1945 (Box 780, Folder 9)
- Cooper, Lane, 1907-1916 (Box 780, Folder 10)
- Horowitz, Elinor Lander, 1965-1977 (Box 780, Folder 11)
- Latham, Lillian Lawrence, 1923 (Box 780, Folder 12)
- Newton, E. Swift, 1921-1941 (Box 780, Folder 13)
- Smith, Payson, 1914-1915; undated (Box 780, Folder 14)
- General, 1914-1940; undated (Box 780, Folder 15)
- Class and College Material (Box 780)
- English Department, 1941-1945; undated (Box 780.1, Folder 1)
- English 27 quiz, 1942 (Box 780.1, Folder 2)
- Honors in English, 1940s (Box 780.1, Folder 3)
- Shakespeare Seminar, 1941-1942 (Box 780.1, Folder 4)
- Shakespeare Seminar, 1941-1942 (Box 780.1, Folder 5)
- Shakespeare Seminar, 1939-1942 (Box 780.1, Folder 6)
- Notes on M.A. thesis, 1948 (Box 780.1, Folder 7)
- Mildred Weeks, Ph.D. exam, 1942-1943 (Box 780.1, Folder 8)
- "Seven Million Dollar Fund", 1944-1947 (Box 780.1, Folder 9)
- Memo (Murphy), undated (Box 780.1, Folder 10)